[Music]
[Applause]
is from Cambridge and Harvard he is
based in Cambridge but for this com I
think you har is that right
hi we have all seen a mous strip haven't
we movie
stri we the movies
it
is the strip that you make by twisting
and gluing the ends of a strip together
now that strip movie strip has only one
side and all that you know this but
let's try something potentially
new let's cut the movie strip in half
first I'm going to make an ordinary
strip it is just straightforwards strip
okay I didn't twist it's not twisted if
I cut this strip along the center line
what's going to
happen what's going to
happen yes it's going
to I think fall into two
parts and so it
does
okay now the let's make a movie
stet I do that but instead of gluing
like this I twist by one well some
people call this half twist but we shall
call it one twist okay so one Twist by
180° not 360° but
180° and I glue the ends so this is the
classical movie strip whose name is on
the Blackboard what happens if if I cut
it along the center
line any
take yes what's your name abs abs so
what's your what's your
guess
itang it will form two entangled strips
so you get two strips but unlike those
two that fell apart from the ordinary
strip they'll be entangled he says any
other takers any other guesses is Justin
here I met Justin a moment ago yeah what
what's your
guess the same it will be the same so
two strips and it will separate into two
and they'll fall
huh which are so they will be entangled
like this but there will be two of them
entangled like this okay any other take
so the same same guess twice any other
guesses you should guess the first
lesson or the zero lesson in mathematics
is that you should always begin by
guessing if possible in
public so that you are committed now you
are interested your Stakes are high and
you have to find out what's going to
happen and you learn much better you see
you're going to spend a year things you
might as well learn this much rather
than this much and the way to learn this
much is to guess and to learn from your
wrong guess es and then build on your
right guesses so any other
guesses huh yes fall apart two parts
will fall apart so there will be two
parts okay you have a guess I think so
the same same thing as those okay so we
have any other guesses any descent okay
shall we do that I start tucking the
center Center Line and probably I should
be singing a song as I do this
I'm cutting cutting cutting and I'm
going all the way around once yeah I'm
about to finish
cutting
ready I
finish I have a single
stre very interesting how did this
happen now I'd like to ask you and
please answer honestly who has seen this
experiment before please raise your
hands who has seen this before some of
you have good okay you see there are
people who have seen this but they may
not have seen the next one how many
twists are there in this strip that we
just obtain it in the initial mov Street
there was one twist okay we count one
how many twists okay let's ask who
thinks it's not Twisted at all zero
twist okay good Brave man who thinks he
has only one twist so it's the same
thing as the original M strip one two
twists okay that's the one that's the
one that most reasonable people go for
congratulations and the logic is
actually not too difficult
to justify you see suppose that this is
a movie strip or just the front of the
movie strip it goes and then twist in
the back and comes back okay
and we are cutting it like this along
the center line and what happened is
that you see if this were not Twisted as
I cut this part will go back and will
connect back to the same
part and this part will go back and will
connect back to the same part but
because it's twisted this part which
goes in the back comes back up but
instead of connecting here gets twisted
and connects to this side and this side
which goes back when it comes back gets
twisted and gets connected to this side
okay so the entire thing get
connected and you have gone around the
strip
twice when you do this this has exactly
twice the length of the original
strip so if the original strip was
twisted once well we went around it
twice so it should be twisted twice also
good who thinks it's twisted three
times four
times some people back there five times
anybody courageous enough to say five
six times I don't have six fingers on my
hand six
[Music]
times okay so we give up how shall we
count this um what is your name s huh s
Sarah can you come up
stage okay so Sarah if you can can be my
assistant thank you very much and hold
this bit of the
strip and I'm going to hold the strip
like this okay and please don't move
even if there's another fire
alarm now this way can you raise your
hand a little bit this way you can see
that all the twists are on the upper
half of the strip and the lower half of
the strip is not Twisted at all so in
order to count how many twist this has
I'm going to don't move
cut the lower half which is irrelevant
which doesn't matter and then start
untwisting the top how many times do I
have to untwist in order to get it
straight that's the number of twists
that the this original this scrip has
okay so how many times don't
move one still
Twisted two well many people voted two
but it's still Twisted that's very
interesting
three look it's still Twisted M finally
four and it's straight four
twists thank you very much we applaud
that why
four we thought well that was logic we
had two twists because movie strip
itself the original one had one twist
and we went around it twice once twice
why not two y4 where do those extra two
4 - 2 extra two twists come
from here is the beginning of a
suggestion suppose that you have again
an ording strip like
this like that I just closed it how many
twists does this have obviously
zero now let's go around it
twice like this do you do you see what
I'm doing
I just went around it twice but without
twisting the
strip I just went around twice but I
didn't twist this strip locally how many
twist does this have I just did the
double of the zero twist does it have
zero twist actually it does have some
twist
look so just by going around the double
double cover is the technical term but
going around double of the zero Twisted
strip you get some twists locally this
is not Twisted but globally it is
interesting that's where the extra two
twists come from because in fact when I
undo it and try to untwist it it turns
out that it's twisted twice okay so just
by going around twice even without any
local twist you get those two extra
twist and those two are added to those
two and you get
four something to
investigate let's
now try something else so far we have
been cutting all the strips along the
center line but suppose that I'm not
very
careful I missed the center line let's
cut the strip along the one3 of the line
you know what I mean so 13 of the
distance from this side in this case we
have that and that and I'm cutting it
along somewhere
here
okay I go up now what's going to happen
any guesses what's going to
happen
huh you have some opinion go ahead four
strips four strips that's very
interesting four strips four
strips okay any other
guesses huh two two two strips okay
shall we vote on the number of strips
first who thinks there will be a single
strip after that's what we got when we
cut the movie strip along the half line
you remember along one half line so one
one strip so several takers thank you
very much two
strips three strips good four there was
some five how about zero stri
okay so let's see what's going to
happen people who said two strips or
more two three four five and so on are
these strips going to fall apart
separate or not no
no why why do they get what's the word
what's your
name huh
ciso ciso what's the word if you want to
express what you're thinking they don't
separate they get what yeah yeah let him
say it they make something like a chain
something like a chain so it's very
heavy no what do you
mean they get well this is your
opportunity to learn a little extra
things so what's the
expression they get
our friend here used the word a moment
ago were you paying attention that was
an opportunity done entangled say that
entangled entangled or linked that's a
more technical term but entangled L
linked and so on okay while I'm
discussing this I went around once but
look do you see I kept cutting along the
third line but I didn't come back to
where I started I came back on the other
side in other words I kept going going
and it got Twisted in the back but when
I came back I came back on this side not
on the left side why is this do we all
understand it yes we do because you see
this line if it the strip were not
Twisted it was an ordinary twist would
just connect back to the same side but
you see it is Twisted so this line which
is on the left hand side gets twisted
and comes connects on the other side so
we have to keep keep cutting we have to
go around
twice so let's keep cutting
again have you made up your mind I'm
about to finish
cutting huh what
what who says
what I keep cutting cutting this is
getting more and more complicated what's
going on here I have no idea what's
going to happen okay are you ready I'm
about to finish cutting nothing up this
seve nothing up this
seve what
happened do we understand this at
all that's there the a long strip and
short strip that are Interlink how many
twists does this one short one
have one in fact you can kind of see
it so do you recognize this this is just
a narrow version of the original movie
strip one twist movie just
narrow how about this long one how many
twist does this
have we should count but it turns out to
have four twists so this two is a narrow
version of Something familiar the result
of the half cut and they are interl why
is
this in order to understand this
let's perturb the parameter that's what
we
say what do I mean by perturbing the
parameter well we cut it along the third
line before we cut it along the half
line but we can cut it
along the line
which is at the distance B from The
Edge okay so the half case corresponds
to D
equals 12 and 1/3 case corresponds toal
1/3 but I can make D any number between
zero and 1 12 it doesn't make sense to
make it larger than2 because I'll be on
the other side okay so what happens if D
is
zero yeah I'm just going just sliding
the scissors along the boundary of the
movie strip I'm I'm not doing anything
essentially what happens when D equals
12 well it's
exactly this single sort of half line
cut that we mentioned
before but in between what's going to
happen well the cuts look like
this okay
let's think about where this strip goes
this part of the strip left half of
strip closer to the closest to the bound
well it goes in the back and then when
it comes back well an a strip would make
it connect back to here but movie strip
twists it and connects it to this part
so this
portion and this portion are connected
to each other and similarly when I go
out over here and come back instead of
connecting back on the right
mov connect it back to here so this is a
single
strip on the other hand what about the
part in the middle middle
part yeah so when it goes out it comes
and it gets twisted but it gets
connected to itself so this is
is its own
component okay now we understand what's
going on you see we did it in the case
of b equal 1/3 but let's make B very
very
small when we make B very very small
what we're doing is
just caressing along the boundary and
not doing anything so we get this middle
yellow piece which is getting fatter and
fatter and
and eventually you get the original
movie
St
yeah or conversely if you make D larger
and larger from zero towards 1/3 we are
just making the original movie strip
narrower narrower narrower until it has
what's the width of the middle piece in
the end when I'm cutting at b equals
1/3
no no if this is 1
[Music]
thir this is also 13 thank you so that's
also
13 okay so what we have here the short
one is just the original mov stri whose
edges have been taken away that's why
you get a copy topologically the same
copy of the original movie strip with
one twist do we understand this other
one we do because that one the long one
corresponds to the pink portion
you see here we examine the case when B
is 1/3 but let's imagine the case when B
is almost
12 that means that this yellow part
becomes narrower narrower narrower okay
and as D converges to 1/2 this yellow
part collapses to a single
line but we know what happens when I cut
it along the single line when we remove
the single line we get a long single
strip with how many twists four twists
so instead of cutting it along a line
let's cut it along a fat
line do you know what I mean so let's
remove the middle portion but what
remains on the side is exactly
topologically the same as the case of
the half cut so this
one in other words this long piece has
also with
1/3 and it is topologically a copy of
the half part so that's why we see this
familiar four twist movie strip and this
familiar one twist movie strip why are
they linked with each other do we know
the gentleman who yawn in the back so
why are they linking each
other why should they be why shouldn't
they fall
apart in order to understand that let's
look at the central piece again this
piece and let's represent it by a single
yellow line I'm going to draw it here
and let's see what the other one is
doing so this yellow line is actually
doing something like this in the
back
okay how is this pink part positioned
with respect to the yellow well for a
while it's running on the left of the
yellow if you
like is it going to join up to the
original bit no no it's going to be
twisted and then join up here so I keep
going and now is it going to be joined
up to this part no it gets twisted again
it crosses over and you see
here it the pink strand goes around the
yellow Center once
and that is exactly the link that you
see
here so we understand a lot about
this
okay let's see what get what we get if
you cut it almost at b equals 1 12 but
not quite what do you
expect it's a revision D is almost 1 12
but a little less than have what do you
expect yeah long four twist and this is
the result it done that you see we see
almost exactly the same thing as in the
first experiment the half cut but here
there's a very very thin version of the
original M which is linked that's this
very thin one is the yellow in the
center okay in
contrast if B is almost equal zero what
do you
get yeah you get all almost the same
thing as the original movie strip almost
you didn't do anything so this is the
result you see you have practically the
original movie strip intact but look
there's something linked to it what is
this well think of it this way think of
the movie strip but think of peeling off
scraping off the boundary and Boundary
comes off and gets link to the m strip
itself and it is Twisted this boundary
bit which is the pink part of the
picture is Twisted how many times four
times thank you very much and it's a
single circle from which by the way we
have learned we discover that the
boundary of a movie strip is a single
Circle am I making sense no I'm not
making sense I didn't understand what I
meant so what do I mean this is an
ordinary strip not not
Twisted what is its boundary well
boundary is the mathematical term for
Edge well there's this
boundary and there's another component
of the boundary this boundary so there
are two separate disjoint circles the
boundary of an ordinary M strip ordinary
strip excuse me is two
circles okay what about the boundary of
a mov
strip I don't have a mov strip anymore
because I cut them
all please ignore this one but it is in
fact boundary this is a mov strip what
is the boundary
you go along the boundary and then to
your surprise you see that the entire
boundary is connected there's only one
Loop who's not convinced please raise
your hands at least half of the class
should be not convinced are you all
convinced you're a bunch of geniuses
okay so so mov strip has a single
boundary Circle okay so that's what
happens okay we understand everything
then let's go back and finish all this
by a little revision you understand now
what happens when you take a movie strip
one twist and then cut it along the
center line right what
happens
huh
sorry no no a single movie strip one
twist and I cut it along with half line
what happens what's your
name huh Z so what happens if you take a
movie strip and cut it along the center
[Music]
line yeah that's a one single strip with
how many twists four twists yes we
understand this yeah of course of course
we all know this because we're are very
clever people and a bunch of geniuses
okay so this is what we get oh what
happened what happened
we got
two components
[Music]
huh and so people back there have an
opinion so what are you
saying what did you say what did you
say tce
say that
again I twisted the original strip twice
instead of
once you you you're saying I'm I
[Music]
cheated respected teacher
do do you think you should disagree with
the
teacher yes you should yes that's what I
did I twisted it twice but that's
interesting right because first of all
some people were taken by surprise haha
but
also exercise or research
project develop a complete theory for
what happens when you take a movie strip
that's Twisted let's say n times and cut
it along a half line or cut it along the
distance D line what's going to happen
what's going to be the
result there should be a very clean
complete description and that's a
wonderful thing to work on let's take a
break for 5 minutes